<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Twelve rules introducting to the art of Latine Composed by Edmund Riue, teacher of the Hebrew &amp;c. in London.</title>
            <author>Reeve, Edmund, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10789</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842147</idno>
  <idno type="VID">6777</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248571388</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21062</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106431</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842147e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Twelve rules introducting to the art of Latine Composed by Edmund Riue, teacher of the Hebrew &amp;c. in London.</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Edmund, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Latin language --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6777:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6777:1"/>
            <p>TWELVE RVLES INTRODVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TING TO THE ART of <hi>LATINE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Composed by <hi>Edmund Riue,</hi> Teacher of the Hebrew &amp;c. in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>ALIIS SERVIEMVS, NOSMETIPSOS CONTERIMVS.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>At London printed by <hi>William Iones.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6777:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6777:2"/>
            <head>Twelue Rules to the Latin.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>AM,</hi> but <hi>ae, ae,</hi> 2. <hi>as,</hi> ac. <hi>am</hi> or <hi>an,</hi> voc. <hi>a.</hi> 3. <hi>es,</hi> ac <hi>en,</hi> voc. &amp; ab. <hi>e</hi> or <hi>a.</hi> 4. <hi>e,</hi> gen. <hi>es,</hi> dat. <hi>e,</hi> ac. <hi>en,</hi> voc. and ab. <hi>e.</hi> 5. <hi>Familias,</hi> after <hi>pater, mater,</hi> or <hi>filius.</hi> 6. <hi>Filia, nata, dea, mula, equa, anima,</hi> and the like, haue dat. and ab. plur <hi>in abus.</hi> 7. <hi>vs,</hi> voc. <hi>e.</hi> 8. <hi>ïus,</hi> of mans proper name, voc <hi>in i.</hi> likewise <hi>filius</hi> and <hi>genius.</hi> 9. <hi>deus,</hi> voc. <hi>Deus,</hi> plur. nom. <hi>dij,</hi> gen. <hi>deorum,</hi> dat. <hi>dijs,</hi> ac. <hi>deos.</hi> 10. <hi>os,</hi> ac. <hi>on,</hi> voc. <hi>e.</hi> but <hi>a pollos,</hi> gen. <hi>o,</hi> voc. <hi>os.</hi> 11. neuters haue nom. ac. and voc. alike, and plurally in <hi>a,</hi> 12. <hi>vis, rauis, tussis, sitis, a mussis, charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, Thamesis,</hi> ac. in <hi>im,</hi> ab. in <hi>i.</hi> 13. <hi>is,</hi> sometimes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue, and moneths names in <hi>er</hi> or <hi>is,</hi> and <hi>centustis,</hi> ab. in <hi>i.</hi> 14. neuters in <hi>al, ar, and e,</hi> ab. in <hi>i,</hi> nom. plur. in <hi>ia,</hi> gen. in <hi>ïum.</hi> sauing <hi>far, hepar, jubar, nectar, gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sape.</hi> 15. nounes in two consonants, or nom. and gen. euan. gen. plur. in <hi>ïum.</hi> so <hi>dis, lis, vis, sal, manes, pena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, linter, uter, as, mas, vas vadis, nox, nix, os, ossis, faux, mus, cor.</hi> 16. but <hi>hyems, princeps, particeps, municeps, forceps, caelebs, cliens, canis, panis, vates, iuvenis, opes, apes, senex, precis, volucris, halcyonis,</hi> and nounes in <hi>er,</hi> haue <hi>um,</hi> but <hi>ales alituum,</hi> and <hi>bos boum,</hi> dat &amp; ab <hi>bobus</hi> or <hi>bubus.</hi> 17. puring Greekes in <hi>is</hi> ac. in <hi>n,</hi> ab. in <hi>i,</hi> plur. gen. in <hi>ïum.</hi> 18. not puring, ac. in <hi>a.</hi> plu. ac. in <hi>as.</hi> 19. Iesus, ac. <hi>um,</hi> else <hi>u.</hi> 20. <hi>acus, lacus, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6777:3"/> arcus, tribus, ficus, specus, quercus, partus, portus, veru,</hi> dat. and ab. <hi>ubus.</hi> 21. Greeke ma, dat. and ab. plur. in <hi>tis.</hi> 22. fift, are feminine, sauing <hi>dies.</hi> 23. sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiuing <hi>occidens, profluens, confluens,</hi> are in g. <hi>consonans, continens,</hi> f. g. <hi>contingens, accidens, ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedens, consequens,</hi> n. g. <hi>appetens, diligens, sitiens, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> c. g. and <hi>animans</hi> f. or n. g. ab. in. <hi>i.</hi> Likewise like. 24. <hi>supellex,</hi> plur. in <hi>ia. rastrum, fraenum, filum, capistrum,</hi> plur. <hi>m,</hi> and <hi>n. coelum,</hi> plur <hi>m. nundinum, epulum, balneum,</hi> plur. f. and <hi>fibilus, iocus, locus,</hi> plur. m. and n. 25. nounes in <hi>i</hi> are inuariable, and in <hi>u,</hi> singularly: and all from three to an hundred .26. <hi>uoctu, natu, iussu, iniussu, promptu, permissu, astu, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> are monoptotes. <hi>fors forte, spontis sponte, repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundarum repetundis, suppetiae suppetias, tantundem tantidem, impetis impete, verberis verbere, vicem vice, plus pluris, iugeris iugere,</hi> are <hi>diptotes:</hi> but these foure are whole plurally. <hi>precis precem prece, opis opem ope</hi> are <hi>triptotes,</hi> but whole plurally. 27. <hi>hordeum, far, forum, mel, mulsum, defrutum,</hi> thus, <hi>soboles, labes,</hi> and all of fift, haue but nom. ac. and voc. plurall: sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>res, species, facie, acies,</hi> and <hi>dies</hi> .28. <hi>laurus, quer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eus, pinus, ficus</hi> a figge or figtree, <hi>lacus, domus, colus, penus, cornus</hi> a dog tree, are in declension second and fourth, some want number, and some redound.</p>
            <p n="29">29. <hi>Totus, solus, nullus, alter, vter, neuter,</hi> and their compounds like <hi>vnus:</hi> but <hi>alius, a, ud.</hi> gen. <hi>alius,</hi> dat. <hi>ii.</hi> 30. <hi>vber</hi> plentiful, <hi>memor, inops, vetus,</hi> pl. neut. in <hi>a,</hi> gen. in <hi>um:</hi> but plura. <hi>ïum.</hi> 31. <hi>hic &amp; haec durior, &amp; hoc durius.</hi> gen. <hi>oris.</hi> dat. <hi>ori.</hi> ac. <hi>hunc &amp; hanc orem, &amp; hoc vs.</hi> voc. m. and f. <hi>or,</hi> and n. <hi>us.</hi> ab. <hi>ore vel ori.</hi> plur. nom. <hi>hi &amp; hae ores, &amp; haec ora,</hi> gen. <hi>orum.</hi> dat. <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6777:3"/> 32. comparatiue is made by adding <hi>or,</hi> to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitiue <hi>i:</hi> and superlatiue <hi>ssimus.</hi> 33. vnto <hi>er,</hi> superlatiue addeth <hi>rimus.</hi> 34. <hi>pureus</hi> increaseth by <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime.</hi> 35. <hi>facilis, gracilis, agilis, docilis, similis, humilis,</hi> change is into <hi>limus,</hi> in superl. 36. of <hi>dico, loquor, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, facio,</hi> comp. is <hi>entior,</hi> superl. is <hi>entissimus.</hi> 37. <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, melior, optimus,</hi> and others anomall in gram. 38. capable participials and aduerbs are compared also. 39. <hi>ille</hi> like <hi>iste,</hi> but <hi>ipse.</hi> neut. <hi>ipsum.</hi> 40. <hi>quis vel qui</hi> as <hi>qui</hi> .41. nom. <hi>quid,</hi> gen. <hi>cuius,</hi> dat. <hi>cui,</hi> ac. <hi>quid,</hi> ab. <hi>quo</hi> .42. <hi>istic, istaec, istoc vel istuc,</hi> ac. <hi>istunc, istanc, istoc, vel istuc.</hi> ab <hi>istoc, istac, istoc.</hi> plur. nom. and ac. n <hi>istaec,</hi> so <hi>illic.</hi> 43. nom. <hi>hiccine, haeccine, hoccine,</hi> ac. <hi>huncci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, hanccine, hoccine.</hi> ab. <hi>hoccine, haccine, hoccine:</hi> plur. nom. and ac. neut. <hi>haeccine.</hi> 44. <hi>ecquis, nequis, nunquis, aliquis, siquis,</hi> haue in nom. fem. sing. and in nom. and ac. neut. plur. <hi>qua.</hi> 45. <hi>vestras</hi> and <hi>cuias</hi> like <hi>nostras:</hi> vocatiues are of the second person, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words of the third, sauing <hi>ego</hi> and <hi>tu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="46">46. Verbs in <hi>ïo</hi> of the third, haue difference in the first rootes formation. 47. <hi>eo, queo, veneo</hi> are pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars 48. the deponent and commune partake of the actiue. 49. <hi>prorsum</hi> afore <hi>e,</hi> assumeth <hi>d.</hi> 50. the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>personall passiue hath an imperatiue pretertence. 51. the syllable doubled in the perfect tence simple, is not in the compound, sauing in <hi>praecurro, excurro, repun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go:</hi> and in the compounds of <hi>do, disco, sco</hi> and <hi>posco.</hi> also the syllables doubled in the perfect tence, is not so in the supine. 52. <hi>Vescor pastus sum, medeor medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus sum, liquor liquefactus sum, reminiscor recordatus sum.</hi> 53. <hi>odi, caepi, memini, noui,</hi> signifie also present-like, &amp; are defectiues like others in gram. 54. <hi>Equet</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6777:4"/> hath no preterperfect tence. <hi>dor, der,</hi> for and his <hi>fer,</hi> are neuer simple. <hi>dic, duc,</hi> and <hi>fac</hi> are imperatiues. 55. The subiunctiue often imperatiuely, and then is vnconiunctioned. 56. <hi>Pariturus, nasciturus, sonaturus, arguiturus, luitutus, erniturus, nosciturus, moriturus, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riturus, osurus, secaturus, affricaturus, refricaturus, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturus, iuvaturus,</hi> proceed anomally. 57. manifold is composition and deriuation. 58. from <hi>itus</hi> or <hi>ctus</hi> of the first, proceedes <hi>atio,</hi> sauing <hi>sectio.</hi> 59. but <hi>tor</hi> thence, is regular. 60. <hi>paenitens, decens, libens, paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendus, pudendus,</hi> doe proceed: so others naturall.</p>
            <p n="61">61. <hi>Nam, quare, ac, ast, atque, et, aut, vel, nec, neque si, quin, quatenus, sin, seu, siue, ni, nisi,</hi> are prepositiues. 62. <hi>quidem, quoque, autem, vero, enim,</hi> are subiunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues. 63. <hi>que, ne, ve</hi> are <hi>enclytickes.</hi> 64. <hi>ante</hi> before in time, <hi>circum</hi> about place, <hi>circa</hi> about place or time, <hi>circiter</hi> about time or number, <hi>secundum</hi> after or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, <hi>vsque</hi> vntill, or well-nye vnto, <hi>secus</hi> by the way, <hi>cum</hi> with together. 65. <hi>am</hi> about, <hi>di</hi> along, <hi>dis</hi> asunder, <hi>re</hi> againe, <hi>se</hi> apart, <hi>con</hi> together with, are compositiues: and <hi>con</hi> afore a vowell or <hi>h,</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth <hi>n.</hi> 66. <hi>a</hi> and <hi>e</hi> afore a consonant, <hi>ab</hi> afore a vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and so <hi>ex</hi> commonly: but <hi>abs</hi> afore <hi>qu</hi> or <hi>t.</hi> and after <hi>x, s,</hi> may be omitted. 66. <hi>quod</hi> that, to the time past or present, and <hi>ut</hi> that, to the time to come. 67. ambiguous ablatiues in <hi>a,</hi> and <hi>hic</hi> here, and <hi>ergo</hi> for the sake are circumflexed. 68. ambiguous indecli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables are in context grauated, but in end acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 69. <hi>fa</hi> in <hi>facio</hi> compounded is vttered long, and <hi>ma</hi> in <hi>amabo</hi> short. 70. a vowell afore <hi>a</hi> vowell is short, except in <hi>sio,</hi> and in the <hi>ïus,</hi> sauing <hi>alterius,</hi> and sauing <hi>e,</hi> between double <hi>i,</hi> in the fift. 71. also a vowel
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6777:4"/> is short afore <hi>a mute</hi> with <hi>a liquid</hi> vnlesse analogy let. 72. a preterperfect tence &amp; supine dissylable is long in <hi>penult,</hi> except in <hi>fidi, bibi, dedi, scidi, steti, tuli:</hi> and in <hi>quitum, situm, litum, itum, rutum, ratum, satum, datum,</hi> and <hi>citum</hi> of <hi>cieo.</hi> 73. <hi>do,</hi> with his compounds hath <hi>a,</hi> short. 74. adiectiues in <hi>inus</hi> product <hi>ï;</hi> except <hi>diutinus crastinus, pristinus, perendinus, hornotinus, serotinus, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaginus, faginus, cedrinus, carbasinus,</hi> and like materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. 75. but originall quantity remaineth. 76. vnto an hundred, the lesse nūber cardinal first with a copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue: otherwise it is latter euery where. 77. <hi>comma</hi> distinguisheth little, <hi>semicolon</hi> somwhat more; <hi>colon</hi> most: but <hi>period</hi> ends. <hi>parenthesis</hi> interposeth omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible. <hi>interrogatiue</hi> asketh, <hi>admiratiue</hi> wondreth or exclaimeth at, <hi>conuinctiue</hi> vniteh, <hi>diuisiue</hi> diuideth, and <hi>apostrophus</hi> pareth.</p>
            <p n="78">78. A <hi>verbe</hi> must be in the same number &amp; person, as his nominatiue case is in. 79. an <hi>a diectiue</hi> must be in the same number, case and gender as his substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue is in. 80. a <hi>relatiue</hi> must be in the same number, gender, and person, as his <hi>antecedent</hi> is in: and the relatiue must be in the nominatiue case vnto the verb next after him, if no nominatiue case be between thē. 81. If a <hi>verb, adiectiue,</hi> or <hi>relatiue</hi> hath before him cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled supposites, he must be plurall, and agree with the worthier. 82. if they be liuelesse, the <hi>adiectiue</hi> or <hi>rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> must commonly be neuter. 83. also they being betweene two supposites may agree with eyther. 84. Also if they respect but to one matter, they must be singular and neuter. 85. but if they to more than to one, they must bee plurall. 87. If a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiue substantiue bee betweene the <hi>relatiue</hi> and the <hi>Verbe</hi> next after him, the <hi>Relatiue</hi> must bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6777:5"/> in that case, as the word whereof he is gouerned will haue him to be in. 87. the <hi>relatiue</hi> may be substantiue vnto the <hi>adiectiue</hi> after him. 88. nounes <hi>interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues</hi> and <hi>indefinitiues</hi> follow the rules and nature of the <hi>relatiue.</hi> 89. in a question, and to an imperatiue verbe, and because of it or there the nominatiue is transposed. 90. the <hi>verbe</hi> is principall, which hath afore him neither <hi>relatiue</hi> nor <hi>coniunction,</hi> and is not infinitiue. 91. When <hi>quod</hi> that, or <hi>ut</hi> that, may be vsed, they may be left out, and then the next nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue following must be in the accusatiue, and the next verb following must be in the infinitiue.</p>
            <p n="92">92. An <hi>adiectiue</hi> hauing the thing or things substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to him, may bee put neuterly, the Latine for thing or things not expressed. 93. and an <hi>adiectiue</hi> being so put, may be <hi>substantiue</hi> to an <hi>adiectiue</hi> after him. 94. also an <hi>adiectiue</hi> may be put neuterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>substantiue,</hi> when as it hath afore it a preposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and aduerbializeth. 95. also if an <hi>adiectiue</hi> haue a liuelesse <hi>substantiue,</hi> it may be neuter, and his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiue be in the genitiue. 96. if any <hi>adiectiue</hi> hath not his <hi>substantiue</hi> expressed in Latine, hee substanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth. 97. a <hi>substantiue</hi> vnderstood to an <hi>adiectiue,</hi> is to be conceiued in like case vnto that <hi>adiectiue.</hi> 98. an <hi>adiectiue partitiue</hi> as of the gender, as the next <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiue</hi> after him is. 99. the casuall word begotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly following a verbe or participle, must be the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiue case, vnlesse a rule beneath letteth, 100. when the gouerning word may be well enough vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, it is in latine commonly omitted: Likewise o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such words are. 1. A <hi>substantiue</hi> is not gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the <hi>adiectiue</hi> afore him, whereunto hee is <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiue,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6777:5"/> but of some ōther gouerning word afore that <hi>adiectiue.</hi> 2. the latter of two <hi>substantiues</hi> diuersing, may be in the genitiue; or rather in his <hi>adiectiue</hi> pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessiue, if good sense permitteth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When vnto <hi>his, her,</hi> or <hi>their</hi> may be added <hi>own,</hi> it must be made by <hi>suus.</hi> 4. when vnto <hi>him, her,</hi> or <hi>them</hi> may be added <hi>selfe</hi> or <hi>selues,</hi> it must be made by <hi>sui.</hi> 5. otherwise <hi>his, her,</hi> or <hi>their</hi> is by a relatiues genitiue. 6. speciall <hi>ownity</hi> is signified by adding <hi>ipsius, solius, vnius, duorum, trium, &amp;c. omnium, plurium, paucorum, cuiusque,</hi> and participles presents genitiues refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly. 7. <hi>ipse</hi> may bee for any person. <hi>hic</hi> sheweth him by me. <hi>iste</hi> him by thee. <hi>ille</hi> him from vs both. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>iste</hi> for contempt, and <hi>ille</hi> for eminencie. 8. <hi>ille</hi> the one, <hi>hic</hi> the other relatiuely. 9. <hi>alius</hi> one, <hi>alius</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonstratiuely. 10. <hi>et</hi> both, <hi>et</hi> and. <hi>vel</hi> either, <hi>vel</hi> or. 11. <hi>as,</hi> after, <hi>talis,</hi> is, <hi>qualis:</hi> after <hi>tantus, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> after <hi>tot, quot:</hi> after <hi>tam, quam:</hi> after <hi>adeo, ac:</hi> after <hi>ita, atque,</hi> with potentiall Latine. 12. after an aduerbe of wishing, and <hi>dum</hi> so, that, or vntill, <hi>quoad</hi> vntill; <hi>quasi, ceu, tanquam, perinde acsi, haud secus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si, quamuis, licet, si</hi> although, <hi>qui</hi> seeing that, <hi>cum</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, forasmuch as, or because; <hi>ne, an, num, utrum,</hi> taken not interrogatiuely; <hi>ut</hi> that, least not, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that, must be potentiall Latine. 13. but after <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec</hi> as long as, <hi>dum</hi> whiles that, <hi>si quis, quando, quandoquidem, quoniam, quippe</hi> without <hi>qui, ne, an, num, vtrum, nonne, anne</hi> interrogatiues; <hi>vt</hi> after that, as, euen as, or how, must be indicatiue latine. 14. <hi>en</hi> and <hi>ecce</hi> shewing, require a <hi>nominatiue;</hi> but vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to an accusatiue. 15. <hi>tempori, luci, vesperi</hi> may <hi>aduerbialize.</hi> 16. after <hi>aduerbs</hi> of quantity, time, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6777:6"/> place, &amp; <hi>instar</hi> and <hi>adiectiues</hi> of likenes may be a geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. 17. and aduerbs may gouern such case, as do the nounes or prepositions whence they come. 18. in, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying on, vpon, towards, against, into or vnto, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an accusatiue. 19. <hi>sub</hi> vnto, by or a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to an accusatiue; <hi>suber</hi> beyond, to an accusatiue, concerning <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>on,</hi> to an ablatiue. <hi>tenus</hi> to an ablatiue singular or plurall, but to a genitiue plurall onely. 20. <hi>cum</hi> with, is set after <hi>ego, tu, sui,</hi> and <hi>qui.</hi> &amp; <hi>tenus, versus, paenes</hi> and <hi>vsque</hi> after all. 21. <hi>o,</hi> to a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiue, accusatiue, and vocatiue. <hi>heu</hi> &amp; <hi>pro</hi> to a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiue or accusatiue, &amp; <hi>pro</hi> to avocatiue. <hi>hei</hi> &amp; <hi>veh</hi> to a datiue. <hi>apage</hi> &amp; <hi>apagete,</hi> &amp; <hi>hem</hi> to an accusatiue.</p>
            <p n="22">22. A casuall word vntokened, after a verbe sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiue. 23. or after a passiue verb of terming .24. or after a verbe of gesture. 25. or after an infinitiue with a verbe of wishing. 26. or after the word beeing. 27. or after an <hi>aduerb</hi> of likenes. 28. or after a <hi>coniunctiō copulatiue, disjunctiue, discretiue</hi> or <hi>exceptiue.</hi> 29. or after a substātiue vncapable <hi>of</hi> of, must be in like case vnto the word afore it. 30. but a casuall word vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, must be in the ablatiue. 31. a casual word of the valew must be in the genitiue, and it hath, or may haue the token as afore it. 32. a casuall word of the property is in the ablatiue or genitine. 33. a casuall word of price is in the ablatiue, sauing <hi>tanti, quanti, pluris, minoris,</hi> and their compounds. 34. yet <hi>valco</hi> may haue an accusatiue. 35. the casuall word signifying part of time is in the ablatiue. 36. but signifying continuall terme of time, is in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusatiue. 37. if it signifie space betweene place and place, it must be in the accusatiue. 38. if it signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the measure of <hi>height, length, depth, breadth, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6777:6"/> vnto an <hi>adiectiue</hi> it must bee in accusatiue or abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. 39. a proper name of a comprehended place, hauing <hi>in</hi> or <hi>at</hi> afore it, must bee in the genitiue. 40. so <hi>humi</hi> on the ground, <hi>domi</hi> in or at <hi>home, militiae, belli,</hi> in or at warre, or warfare. 41. but if it be plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or of the third declension, it must bee in the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or ablatiue. so <hi>ruri vel ruro,</hi> in or at the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. 42. and hauing to afore it, it must be in the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiue: so <hi>domum,</hi> home or to home: <hi>rus,</hi> to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. 43. and hauing from or by afore it, must bee in the ablatiue: likewise <hi>domus</hi> and <hi>rus</hi> are vsed. 44. the casuall word of the crime may be in the ablatiue or genitiue. 45. but with <hi>vterque, nullus, alter, neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, alius, ambo,</hi> or a superlatiue, it must be in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue onely. 46. also the casuall word signifying the measure of exceeding, or the forme or manner of a thing, after a verbe or noune, must be in the abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue also.</p>
            <p n="47">47. <hi>of</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> after a participle passiue, or adiectiue in <hi>bilis,</hi> is token of the <hi>datiue.</hi> 48. but after a verbe passiuall is commonly <hi>à,</hi> and sometimes token of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. 49. <hi>of,</hi> after <hi>opus</hi> and <hi>vsus</hi> need, is token of the ablatiue. 50. and of, after verbs or adiectiues, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>fulnesse, emptinesse, plenty</hi> or <hi>wanting, loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> or <hi>vnloading,</hi> is of ablatiue or genitine. 51. like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise after <hi>dignus</hi> and <hi>indignus.</hi> 52. but of, after <hi>natus, prognatus, satus, creatus, cretus, ortus, editus, generatus,</hi> is of the ablatiue. 53. after <hi>pertaesus,</hi> is in the accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. 54. but <hi>indoctus</hi> &amp; <hi>inexpertus</hi> require a genitiue: and <hi>fretus</hi> an ablatiue. 55. of or concerning is <hi>de</hi> 56. <hi>of</hi> or <hi>from,</hi> after verbs of receiuing, distance or taking away is <hi>à:</hi> and sometimes is taken of the datiue.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6777:7"/> 57. but of, or out of, is <hi>e.</hi> 58. and of, after <hi>dignor, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero,</hi> or <hi>communico,</hi> is of the ablatiue. 59. and after <hi>mereor,</hi> is <hi>de.</hi> 60. <hi>To,</hi> after a verb or participle of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto, is <hi>ad.</hi> 61. and to, vnable to be of, after a substantiue is <hi>ad.</hi> 62. &amp; to, after <hi>attinet, pertinet, spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat,</hi> is <hi>ad</hi> also. 63. to, not <hi>acquisitiuely</hi> after <hi>natus, commodus, incommodus, propensus, vtilis, invtilis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemens, aptus, conduco, confero, is</hi> ad. 64. <hi>for</hi> or <hi>to,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitiuely, is of the datiue. 65. likewise if for, may be <hi>a,</hi> or thee, following <hi>sum,</hi> or any other verb hauing a datiue. 66. but for or vnto, following or beginning a speech, must be <hi>ad.</hi> 67. <hi>if for,</hi> may be in stead of, or in defence of, it is <hi>pro.</hi> 68. if for may be by reason of, it is <hi>propter</hi> or <hi>ob.</hi> 69. but for, implying the cause. 70. and with implying the instrument or manner of doing, or matter of being, after verbs or adiectiues, is of the ablatiue. 71. <hi>in,</hi> after <hi>desipio, ango, pendeo, discrucior,</hi> is token of the genitiue. 72. and <hi>in,</hi> after verbs or adiectiues, afore a substantiue, wherein is the property or passion, is token of the ablatiue. 73. likewise when it signifieth not act in a place, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 74. <hi>by</hi> or <hi>than</hi> after cōparatiues, are token of the ablatiue. 75. <hi>adiectiues</hi> signifying desire, knowledge, remembrance, &amp; contrary to these and <hi>adiectiues</hi> in <hi>ax</hi> do gouern a genitiue. 76. adiectiues signifying profit likenes, pleasure, submission, relation to any thing, or their contraries, &amp; adiectiues cōpounded with <hi>con,</hi> do gouern a datiue. 77. <hi>cōmunis, immunis, alienus</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strued with a <hi>genitiue, datiue, or ablatiue</hi> preposition'd.</p>
            <p n="78">78. The substantiue after <hi>misereor, miseresco, interest, refert,</hi> &amp; <hi>est</hi> it behoueth, skilleth or concerneth, <hi>sum</hi> sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying to pertaine or for possession, as <hi>satago,</hi> is in the genitiue. 79. but <hi>mine, thine, his owne, our, your, &amp;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6777:7"/> whose behalfe;</hi> or <hi>mee, thee, himselfe, vs, you, whom,</hi> after those impersonals, is to be in the ablatiue, femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine, singular. 80. the casuall word after <hi>reminiscor, obliuiscor, recorder</hi> and <hi>memini,</hi> is in genitiue or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiue. 81. but after <hi>noceo, parco, faueo, indulgeo, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceo, displiceo, adulor, palpor, blandior, libet, dolet, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit, licet, &amp;c.</hi> must be in the datiue. 82. and after verbs betokening to <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>disprofit, to compare, to giue</hi> or <hi>restore, to promise</hi> or <hi>pay, to command</hi> or <hi>shew, to trust, to obey</hi> or <hi>be against, to threaten,</hi> or <hi>to be angry with,</hi> and their compounds, and after <hi>sum,</hi> or his cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds except <hi>possum,</hi> and after verbs compounded with <hi>satis, bene, male, ad, con, sub, ante, post, ob, in, inter,</hi> or <hi>prae,</hi> answering vnto whom, or to what, must be in the datiue. 83. but after <hi>praeco, anteo, praecedo, praeuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, praecurro, praeuincio, laedo, studeo, iuvo, &amp;c.</hi> may be in the accusatiue. 84. so must it it be after <hi>exosus</hi> and <hi>perosus</hi> actiues. 85. and the casuall word vntokened after the accusatiue with a verbe of asking, teaching, araying, or calling, or with <hi>celo, presto, facio,</hi> must be in the accusatiue. 86. and the casual word after <hi>sono, simulo, oleo, viuo,</hi> must be in the accusatiue. 87. but after <hi>tempero moderor,</hi> in the datiue or accusatiue. 88. <hi>cōsulo,</hi> I ask counsel to to an accusatiue, I giue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell to a datiue. 89. <hi>ausculto,</hi> I hear to an accusatiue, I obey to a datiue. 90. <hi>memini,</hi> I mencion, is with <hi>de.</hi> 91. I conquer to a genitiue, I obtain to an abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. 92. <hi>est</hi> and <hi>suppetit</hi> for <hi>habeo,</hi> require the seeming accusatiue to be nominatiue, and the seeming nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue to be datiue. 93. <hi>do tibi literas</hi> for to carry thē. <hi>do ad te literas</hi> for to read them. 94. <hi>metuo, timeo, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mido tibi vel de te,</hi> for thy good. but <hi>te</hi> or <hi>a te</hi> lest thou hurt me. 95. <hi>interdico</hi> may haue an ablatiue after a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>datiue. 96. the casuall word after <hi>vtor, abutor, fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6777:8"/> fruor, laetor, gaudeo</hi> within or at, <hi>muto</hi> with for or with, <hi>nitor,</hi> with, on, or in, <hi>epulor, vescor, glorior, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, supersedeo,</hi> must be in the ablatiue. 97. <hi>oportet</hi> must, to an accusatiue, <hi>licet</hi> may, to adatiue. 98. a verbe cōpound importing motion to, oftentimes may haue after him the case, which his preposition requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. 99. and a verb compound with <hi>a, ab, ad, con, de, e, ex,</hi> or <hi>in,</hi> may sometimes haue after him the casuall word with his preposition afore him also. 100. the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusatiue that may be after a <hi>gerund</hi> in <hi>di,</hi> may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be a genitiue. 1. an impersonall passiue with an ablatiue and <hi>a,</hi> signifieth like his actiue, and this actiues nominatiue, and one verbe or adiectiue, may at one time gouerne diuers cases.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The actiue infinitiue present tence english, after a substantiue of property, or after <hi>cupidus, peritus, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quarus,</hi> and their compounds, must be gerund in <hi>di.</hi> 3. which gerund in <hi>di,</hi> hath somtimes <hi>of</hi> or <hi>in</hi> afore it, &amp; then hath participle prsent tence english. 4. but that infinitiues english after another manner substā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or adiectiue must be <hi>gerūd</hi> in <hi>dum,</hi> with <hi>ad</hi> afore it. 5. yet after <hi>dignus, indignus, contentus</hi> and <hi>audax,</hi> it remaines infinitiue present tence. 6. but shewing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son after a speech, must pe in <hi>dum,</hi> with <hi>ad, ob, propter, inter</hi> or <hi>ante</hi> afore it. 7. and the infinitiue passiue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent tence after <hi>dignus, indignus, turpis, foedus, procli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, facilis, odiosus, mirabilis, optimus,</hi> &amp; the like may be in the latter supine, or in the infinitiue passiue. 8. but after vnlike <hi>adiectiues</hi> must be the <hi>gerund</hi> in <hi>dum</hi> with <hi>ad</hi> afore it. 9. the participle of the present tence eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, with <hi>of</hi> or <hi>with,</hi> or <hi>for</hi> afore it, after a noune ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue must be gerund in <hi>do.</hi> 10. likewise wheresoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it may haue in or by afore it. 11. and if that english
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6777:8"/> may haue afore it the english of <hi>à, e, cum, in,</hi> or <hi>pro,</hi> they are to bee vsed afore it. 12. and if it begetteth a casuall word, it may be made to agree with it. 13. likewise may that which might be the <hi>gerund</hi> in <hi>dum,</hi> with a preposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion afore it. 14. must or ought vnto a verbe, may be by <hi>gerund</hi> in <hi>dum,</hi> and the verbe <hi>est,</hi> in his proper mood &amp; tence, and the <hi>doer</hi> in the datiue. 15. all the gerunds may be vsed passiuely, and yet in the aforesaid gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="16">16. A casual word after a substantiue in the beginning of a speech, is to be in the accusatiue. 17. the <hi>optatiue</hi> mood is sometimes vsed without an aduerb of wishing expressed to it. 18. that which may be vttred in a word may somtimes be vy phrase &amp; sometimes by variation. 19. sense may deriue larine, &amp; may rightly ioyne it, and may discern of it. 20. <hi>consonant</hi> it to follow <hi>vowell,</hi> and <hi>vowell</hi> after <hi>consonant,</hi> according to the eare, &amp; latines nature: but the verb is to be last in speech, or a <hi>polysil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable</hi> of long <hi>penult.</hi> 21. <hi>archaismes, varieties, figures,</hi> and <hi>poeticals</hi> are to be obserued. 22. for to construe latine, first I must read the sentence to a ful point, marking al the points &amp; proper names: secondly, I must take first a vocatiue case, if there be any one; or whatsoeuer is in stead of it, and that which depends of it, for to make it plaine: thirdly, I must seek out the principall verb, and his nominatiue case, &amp; take first the nominatiue case, or whatsoeuer is in stead of it, &amp; that which hangeth on it, for to make it plaine: then the verbe with the infinitiue mood, or <hi>aduerb:</hi> &amp; next the accusatiue case, or such case as the verb properly gouerns: lastly, all the other cases in order: as 1. the <hi>genitiue;</hi> 2. the <hi>datiue;</hi> 3. the <hi>ablatiue,</hi> according as good sense, and parsing will suffer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>